<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes out of France. On the first of this moneth of March Wherein is set downe, the retiring of the Prince of Parma, and the great losse that he hath receiued in the same. Also a true report of a great galley that was brought to Rochell on the sixt of Februarie last.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117836</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853046</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853046</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1545:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes out of France. On the first of this moneth of March Wherein is set downe, the retiring of the Prince of Parma, and the great losse that he hath receiued in the same. Also a true report of a great galley that was brought to Rochell on the sixt of Februarie last.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [3], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde by William Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part 2 has separate register and pagination and separate dated title page that reads: The true report of a great galley that was brought vnto Rochell, vpon the sixt of Februarie last. 1592.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alessandro Farnese, --  Duke of Parma, 1545-1592.</term>
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18409:1"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:18409:1"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
                  <p>Newes out of France.</p>
                  <p>ON THE FIRST OF this moneth of March.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is ſet downe, the retiring of the Prince of Parma, and the great loſſe that he hath receiued in the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo a true report of a great Galley that was brought to Rochell on the ſixt of Februarie laſt.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>French royal fleur-de-lis</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſolde by William Wright. 1592.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18409:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18409:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
                  <head>Newes out of Fraunce, on the firſt <hi>of March. 1592.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Troubles of <hi>Fraunce</hi> grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a popular diſcontent of ſundrie ill affected perſons to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their naturall Liedge king, in that hee ſéekes to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw them from mans traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the puritie of the goſpel, ſhewes not onely the long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance of God towards the wicked, but his iuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vppon ſtubborne and head-ſtrong Nations, that hearken not vnto the voyce of the charmer, charme he neuer ſo wiſelie. Yet the ſundrie victories the French King hath had againſt his enemies, diſcouers not only the equitie of his cauſe, but aſſured teſtimonie that God will pull down the plumes of ſuch rebellious ſubiects as reſiſt the Lords annointed.</p>
                  <p>A manifeſt inſtance of the which fell out of late, by a great victorie the French Kinges forces hath had againſt the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> which was in this maner. The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> intrenched himſelfe ſtrongly by <hi>Noue Chaſtell</hi> not far from <hi>Deepe,</hi> whereof <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Vitrey</hi> was Gouernour, and there in warlike manner fortified himſelfe with Baricados and other muniments to withſtand the ſodaine inuaſion of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: yet neither ſo warilie, nor ſo ſtrongly, but the kings forces plaid vpon him ſo hard, that what inforced
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18409:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
by the Kings power, whoſe valour was more then his multitudes, and drawen on by a mutinie of the french companies that were with him, who could not brooke the imperious gouernment of the proud Spaniard, he was conſtrained to breake vppe his trench and retire home-ward as well as hee might for his owne ſafety. For though hee had ſundrie Squadrons of the French that were both the Kings profeſſed enemies, and of the Leagar: yet the French Gentlemen béeing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what haughtie of themſelues, did with the more impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſuffer the inſolence of the commaunding and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-wéening Spaniards. Where vppon the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> grew offended, and for that ſpeciall reaſon reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as he did manifeſt in a letter ſent to <hi>Mounſieur de Villiers</hi> gouernour of <hi>Roan</hi> for the Leager, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents whereof are theſe.</p>
                  <p>I came to aid you, but I could not performe what I intended, for that I cannot aſſure my ſelfe of the French, who (as I am not their maiſter, ſo they will not obey me, which occaſion mooues me thus ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to depart: but I meane to returne againe ſhortlie, with greater forces and more ſtrength, and ſuch as ſhall obey me. Wherefore, I pray you continue ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and be of good comfort. Yet had there not bene a more ſpeciall reaſon, happilie he would haue taken order both to haue quieted the French gentlemen, and haue gotten more ſupplies to haue counteruailed the Kinges power: but God who is called therefore, the Lord of hoaſts, becauſe hee hath victorie in his hand to ſuppreſſe and conquer at his pleaſure, ſtretched out a mightie arme againſt the Duke, and as hee puniſhed <hi>Pharao</hi> with plagues for his diſobedience, ſo hee ſent a gréeuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſcarcitie, darth, and famin amongſt the dukes forces, not onely for victuals, which though they were extreamelie ſcant, and that the ſouldiers were ſo pined
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18409:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
and almoſt weakned euen to the death, that the gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their bowels began to bréed the bloudie-flixe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: but their greateſt plague was, that ther was no prouiſion for his horſe, neither prouand, hey, ſtubble, nor ſtraw: in ſo much that as much hay as is ſould in England for 4. pence, was worth there euen at the Dukes owne hands 40. ſhillings, which famin lighting amongſt the horſes, bred ſuche mortall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion amongeſt them, that ſuch as died not (as there periſhed dailie multitudes of them) had ſtraunge and ſundry diſeaſes, eſpecially there grew out of their ſides great ſwellinges like wens, which going in againe, ſtraight kild them, and being dead, their fleſh ſo ſtunk, that it bred a mortality amongſt the ſouldiers. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may ſée the iuſt iudgement of God, that kicke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pricke, and reſiſt a manifeſt truth, vnto the maintenance of their papiſticall and ceremonious reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> driuen thus to retire, ſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him to take vp a conuenient place to lodg his men in: ſome 400. horſemen, and 800. footmen, but <hi>Mounſ. de Longueuille</hi> hearing how they marcht, although his power was but ſmall, yet vpon a zeale to God, his Liege and Countrey, with a determined reſolution ſet vppon them, and in ſhort time, diſcomfited them, &amp; put all of them to the ſword. Which newes being brought to the Duke of <hi>Parmas</hi> eares, hee began ſtraight to doubt of himſelfe, and after conſultation had for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſafetie, hee retreated in one night ſeauen leagues, and ſo hee concluded to paſſe ouer the riuer of <hi>Soan</hi> at <hi>Amiens,</hi> and his companie to get ouer the riuer at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beuille,</hi> making ſuch great haſt, that in the way he left behind many Charets and Waggens: in ſome place four, in other ſixe, and other whiles ten: to the number of 200. and more: rather yéelding ſuch luggage a pray
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18409:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
to the enemies then anie more of his forces ſhould bee impaired. The King hearing of the Duke of <hi>Parmas</hi> retire, or rather ſodaine eſcape (to ſhadowe his flight with more honourable names) leauing <hi>Roan</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlie blockt vp with troupes and men of reſolution to leager it in his abſence: amongſt whom <hi>Mounſieur de Giury</hi> was one. Then in his owne perſon marcht for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward after the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> accompanied with a braue troupe of horſe, with intent to fight with the Duke if by any means he might chance to méet him in his iorney.</p>
                  <p>After the Duke thus had made his retire from <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Chaſtell, Mounſieur de Vitrey</hi> the gouernor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of yéelded both it and himſelfe and all his ſouldiers, to the number of a hundreth to the mercy and fauour of the King, who receiued him with al acuſtomed clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Beſide that, moſt part of the French Gentlemen that were of the Leager, whether toucht in conſcience that they ſtriue againſt their lawfull Soueraigne, or doubting that God wil ſo fauour the kings forces that his enemies ſhall goe by the worſt, as daily they doe. Well howſoeuer moued I know not, but they make continuall ſute to the king to haue a paſſeport to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelues to their houſes, promiſing neuer to beare armes any more, except it bee in his Maieſties ſeruice, and alwayes and in all places to bee ready to execute any thing his Highnes ſhall commaund them: but how the king accepts of their ſute, we haue not as yet any certaine intelligence: where we may note that although they haue continued long mutinous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Maieſtie, yet at laſt, the touch of their own guilty minds makes them in a tremblinge forme of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſue for fauour at his handes, whome ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly, they haue hetherto rebelled againſt.</p>
                  <p>Of theſe French gentlemen that had bene with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18409:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> three hundred very well horſt, drew themſelues toward <hi>Roan,</hi> and by the way were all ouerthrowne and ſlaine.</p>
                  <p>Further when the king was remoued with ſome of his forces to follow the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> they of the <hi>Faulcon</hi> which is a Caſtell ſcituate neere vnto <hi>Roan,</hi> did come forth with two hundreth horſe, to geue an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt vpon the kinges power that was left behinde, euery man promiſing to himſelfe, large ſpoyles out of the kinges tentes, but it fell out contrary to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, for <hi>Monſieur de Giury,</hi> being by ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete eſpials, forewarned of this, was not onely in a readineſſe to receiue them, but laide diuers ambuſhes to circumuent them, placing ſome ſhotte ſo cunningly and cloſely, that they found as ſharpe intertainemente as might bee, for the kinges power brake out vppon them before, and the ſhot ſo galled the horſe on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, that of two hundred, there eſcaped away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, but ſeauenteene perſons, to the great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the kinges part, and the diſmay of them in <hi>Roan.</hi> Thus doth the Lord helpe the cauſe of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and breakes the iaw-bones of his enemies, and brings his foes to confuſion, Farewell.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18409:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
                  <pb facs="tcp:18409:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
                  <p>THE TRVE REPORT OF a great Galley that was brought <hi>vnto Rochell, vpon the ſixt of</hi> Februarie laſt. 1592.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of a ship in full sail</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by Iohn VVolfe. 1592.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18409:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18409:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
                  <head>The true report of a great Galley, <hi>that was brought to Rochell, on the</hi> 6. of Februarie laſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we enter with déepe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to cenſure of the late pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſperitie of the Spaniards, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hard fortune inflicted vpon them by God for their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt oppoſing themſelues againſt the truth and his Goſpell: wee ſhall find that their ſundrie miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps preſageth their fall to be néere, and that their ſins being ripe, wrath cannot long be deferd. But as <hi>Silo,</hi> ſo their pride ſhall vaniſh like a ſmoke, and their ruine ſhall be like the deſtruction of thoſe fiue Citties, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fiue righteous perſons could not be found out. The wealth of Tyre, the glorie of Sidon, the pompe of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom could not ſaue them from incurring the fatal iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods wrath, becauſe they had eaten ſower grapes, and their childrens teeth were ſet on edge: ſo that they deliuered ſinnes to their poſteritie, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed the almightie from generation to generation. euen ſo, the Spaniards gilden mines, their hauty ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes, their honors, their worldly glories, no not the praiers of their Cardinals, Abbots, Moonks, and Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, their <hi>Agnus dei,</hi> their holy water, and ſuch traſh, cannot with-hold the wrath of God from them, while
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18409:7"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
any ſaid, they kicke againſt the pricke, and are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt perſecutors of his truth and religion, but he driues them on by degrees, to féele the daunger of their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned deſtruction: and to ſhew you an inſtance what happened to them of late, it fell out thus.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Brittanie</hi> the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> had two great Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſes and foure Gallies, the which hee appointed to kéepe the ſeas vpon the coaſt of Brittanie, and ſo along from S. <hi>Malo</hi> to <hi>Rochel.</hi> Of theſe in Nouember laſt returned into Portingall the two Galeaſſes and one Galley. Of the three Gallies that remained, this that was brought into Rochell was the Admirall, this gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley had fiue and twentie oares of a ſide, and to euerie oar was chained fiue ſlaues to row them, and was left Admirall for thoſe which remained behind. Shee bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing verie wel prouided, both of victuals, ordinance, and other furniture of warre, hauing within her both ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners &amp; ſouldiers about 500. men, ſome Spaniards, others Portingals, but the greateſt number were of Spaine. But their imperious commandings (as the Spaniard is moſt inſolent) drew theſe two nations to a ſecret tumult and priuate mutinie, eſpecially ſeeing rancour yet remained in the hearts of the Portingals, for their late abuſe offered to their king <hi>Don Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> and a mortall hatred fretted the mind of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, leaſt the Portingall might in time make recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of their loſſes. Enuie thus burning in both partes, it grew vnto ſuch a controuerſie, that the matter was faine to bee taken vp by the chiefe Captaine and other principall Gentlemen and officers in the ſaide Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</p>
                  <p>The Captaine being a Spaniard, and his Ancient beeing Portingall, vppon this ſpeciall mutinie that grewe thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gh vnknowen grudges, dealt ſo with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading reaſons and faire ſpéeches, that betweene
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18409:7"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
them two, they appeaſed the brawle, and ſet downe a preſent order for puniſhing of the chiefe offenders: ſo that preſently there were hanged thrée Portingals, to the great terrour and affrighting of the reſt. They in the Galley, looking when anye of the Spaniardes ſhould be hanged for the ſame offence: but ſéeing no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meant by the Captaine, to the puniſhment of the Spaniard, the Ancient-bearer tooke it in verie il part, and the more, that the Captaine vttered ſome woords of diſgrace againſt the Portingals and their king. The want of execution, and the opprobrious ſpéeches vſed to himſelfe and the ſtate of Portingall, made the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to murmure, which the Captaine perceiuing, drew to Bell Iſle, there to prouide better for his ſafetie: but the Ancient being as politicke as he was, prouidently prooued to take occaſion as fitted his turne, firſt to deale with the Marriners, who were the rather pliant to his motion, in that they were Portingals: ſo that hee wan them eaſilie to the reſolute execution of his purpoſe, which was to be reuenged fatally vpon the ſpaniards: hauing thus brought the Marriners to his contented determination, he then broake with the Turkes, &amp; the other ſlaues that were in the Galley, promiſing them their libertie if they would ſticke to him, and followe his aduice: the poore, whom ſeruile bondage had déep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie tormented, beeing in a ſecond hell vppon earth, and glad to bee deliuered from his thraldome, agréed all in one ſimpathie of mind, and ioyfullie praied and wiſhed for fit and conuenient oportunitie. In this hope it ſo fell out, that they came to Bell Iſle, according vnto the cheife Captaines determination, where hee with diuers other Spaniards of moſt account, went on land thinking themſelues to bee ſafe when they were there ariued, going merrily to their friendes to bee frolicke. The Ancient careful, taking time by the forehead, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18409:8"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
the moſt of the Spaniards to bee a ſléepe by weari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of ſome ſeruice: they had before deliuered ares vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ſlaues which were Turks, Portingals, &amp; french men, therewith to vnlooſe and breake their chaines when ſome of the Spaniards perceiued that weapons were deliuered vnto the ſlaues, they began to be feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſuſpitious of ſome preſent mutinie. But while they were in this dumpe, they were preſently ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon by the Ancient-bearer, Portingals, Turkes, and Frenchmen his confederates. The Spaniards deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſéeing flight could not helpe them, ſtucke to their tackling, and fought luſtelie: but the Auncient-bearer armed with reuenge, buckled himſelfe to the ſkirmiſh and though he were ſore wounded, yet hee ſlew three-ſcore perſons, and with the helpe of the ſlaues, put all the Spaniards to the ſword, and ſo hoiſing ſailes, bent their courſe towardes <hi>Don Anthonie</hi> their King in England. But as they were in this hope, the winde came about and blew contrarie, ſo that they were fain to put into the haye of Rochell. On the ſixt day of Februarie, where after diſcourſe made of their preſent fortunes, they were well entertained of the French. The Auncient-bearer offering in his name, and the reſt their ſeruice to the King in theſe his wars againſt the Leagars, graunting in forme of a frée gift their Galley, ordinance, and all other prouiſion. The barke had ſtore of ordinance of great value, in ſo much that diuers which wer aboord on her, ſaid: that ſhe had ſtore of field péeces, all caſt in braſſe, which were carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Rochell to the Kings vſe. Aboue the reſt, there was one thing wondrous and worth the noting, that the Lanthorne that gaue her light, was valued worth 500. pound and few or none ſuch beeing euer ſéene in Chriſtendom before, it was giuen to the French king for a iewell. Then if the Lanthorne were of ſuch coſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18409:8"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
the wealth of the ſhip is more eaſilie to be coniectured. Beſide ſhe had great ſtore of wine and other victuals, ſo that it was imagined, that this ſpring ſhee ſhoulde haue made for new-Hauen in the riuer of <hi>Roan.</hi> But now ſhe lieth tied within the chains of <hi>Rochel,</hi> There came out of her great ſtore of people, among the which were many ſpaniſh women or groſſe widowes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it is reported, that in great brauerie the Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall is gone to the French King, and all the Turkes and other ſlaues vncommitted and ſet at liberty, to the great ioy of all good chriſtian hearts, that ioy to heare, either the controuerſie or confuſion of the Spaniards. Thus you heare how God deliuered the Portingals and poore ſlaues from thraldome by a priuate mutiny, as hee ouerthrew the pride of Babell, whereby we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this comfort, that as GOD cheriſheth his choſen people, ſo hee will confound the deuiſes of ſuch as are oppoſed enemies to his truth and glorie.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>mythological beast's head</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
